ajitjaincse@gmail.com https://ajitjain.github.io

Ajit Jain

ABOUT

Computer Science Ph.D. with 15+ years of experience in conceptualizing, developing, and evaluating state-of-the-art solutions, connecting ideas from human-computer interaction, artificial intelligence, information retrieval, information visualization, and software engineering.

7+ years of experience in managing people, helping them grow and realize their potential. Both as an individual contributor and manager, I have helped create a culture of excellence in the teams I have been a part of, taking them to new heights and delivering unprecedented value to stakeholders.

Citations: 170+ (Google Scholar: https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=B8H-aLkAAAAJ)

- → Best Paper Honorable Mention Award at ACM Creativity & Cognition
- → Best Paper Nomination, Best Student Paper Nomination at ACM Document Engineering

EDUCATION

Texas A&M University

College Station, USA

2015-2021

Ph.D. in Computer Science

Co-Advisors: Dr. Andruid Kerne and Dr. Ruihong Huang

Thesis: How to Support Situated Design Education through AI-Based Analytics

Texas A&M University

College Station, USA

M.S. in Computer Science

2011 - 2014

Advisor: Dr. Andruid Kerne

Thesis: TweetBubble: A Twitter Extension Stimulates Exploratory Browsing

Delhi Technological University

Delhi, India

B.E. in Information Technology

2003-2007

INDUSTRY EXPERIENCE

Full-Time

Oakton, USA Audigent Mar 2022-Present

Distinguished Engineer / Senior Engineer, Data Architecture & Research

- → Led state-of-the-art technology solutions critical to driving executive strategy, conceptualizing and developing them in collaboration with stakeholders across business units.
- → Researched, developed, and productionized new techniques, including AI/ML approaches, for cookieless audiences, audience search, audience configuration, and yield optimization.
- → Filed a patent titled Systems and Method for Simultaneous Relevance and Variety Control in Audience Targeting, addressing the dual needs of scale and specificity.
- → Led and presented Cognitive Audiences technology, a novel, ID-less, turnkey solution addressing 3P cookie deprecation. Launched in collaboration with Experian, the largest credit bureau in the US.
- → Increased revenue—including creation of new revenue streams—through novel cookieless audience solutions, audience curation platforms, and scale maximization approaches.
- → Awarded with spot bonus for scale maximization work toward addressing the simultaneous needs for scale and specificity in audience targeting.
- → Designed, developed, and optimized large-scale data systems focused on deriving audience analytics and presenting them via dashboards.

→ Mentored junior engineers in designing and implementing automation, optimization, and analysis processes.

Amobee Los Angeles, USA

Software Engineer, Data Systems

Jun 2021–Mar 2022

- → Collaborated with stakeholders across business units to identify and disambiguate requirements, as well as to validate that the developed solutions meet or surpass the requirements.
- → Designed, developed, and optimized data pipelines that operate at petabytes scale and deliver ad insights for a range of platforms, including digital and linear media.
- → Created a 4x faster cross-channel report generation workflow, while also eliminating the need for manual intervention at various steps.
- → Investigated machine learning models to optimize data pipeline performance, following extraction of novel insights through exploratory data analysis.
- → Mentored junior engineers in developing and optimizing data pipelines for delivering diverse analytics.

Samsung Noida, India

Lead Engineer / Senior Engineer / Software Engineer

Jul 2007-Aug 2011

- → Played an instrumental role in the commercialization of Java platform for mobile, set-top, and blu-ray product lines, coordinating development across teams in India and S. Korea. Teams' size: 10 members each.
- → Published a first-author research paper at IEEE U-Media titled Modified Programming Language Framework for IVRS Accessibility of Graphical User Interfaces.
- → Developed, ported, and optimized 2D Graphics module of Java Virtual Machine. Created novel MNG animation support in the graphics layer.
- → Mentored junior engineers in implementing graphics rendering and optimizing multithreaded execution.
- → Developed notebook apps focused on remote access and network management, including a Six Sigma project addressing remote desktop performance.
- → Awarded with 'Best Attitude' and 'Extra Mile' awards for outstanding performance and contribution.
- → Developed a web-based software component quality evaluation system, including metrics such as SLOC, coupling, cohesion, and cyclomatic complexity.

Internship

Research Intern

Centrum Wiskunde & Informatica

Amsterdam, Netherlands

Summer 2018

Mentors: Dr. Pablo Cesar and Dr. Abdallah El Ali

- → Identified a research gap in supporting personal health tracker users in understanding their data.
- → Developed surveys to gather needs and evaluate visualizations for users' sensemaking of their sleep data.
- → Identified effective visualizations for sleep tracking through quantitative and qualitative data analyses.

Adobe Research
Data Scientist Intern
Summer 2017

Mentor: Dr. Eunyee Koh

→ Identified a research problem in audience segmentation, engaging in discussions with marketing experts.

- → Developed interactive visualization of large-scale graph data to present audience overlaps across campaigns.
- → Established the system's efficacy through user studies followed by quantitative and qualitative data analyses.

Google Mountain View, USA

Software Engineering Intern

Summer 2016

Mentor: Amos Yoffe

- → Developed module for presenting message results in Android In Apps search, clustered by topic and time.
- → Validated the new presentation method by creating a test dataset of messages and comparing search results.
- → Launched in September 2016, making the feature available worldwide.

Google Summer of Code Student Developer Intern

College Station, USA

Summer 2012

Host Organization: Interface Ecology Lab, Texas A&M University

→ Developed a RESTful service for meta-metadata structured web semantics represented in XML / JSON format.

- → Developed caching, database integration, logging, testing, and deployment modules.
- → Deployed the service in a production environment following a thorough investigation of available web servers.

ACADEMIC RESEARCH PROJECTS

• Design Analytics [Human-Computer Interaction, Artificial Intelligence]

Spring 2017–Spring 2021

A human-centered AI investigation for assisting instructors in assessing a range of visual and conceptual characteristics present within student design work.

- → Engaged co-design discussions and workshops to understand instructors' situated practices and needs.
- → Developed a first-of-its-kind AI recognizer to measure students' use of space and scale in their free-form design work.
- → Deployed AI-based analytics via dashboards, as a technology probe, in situated course contexts.
- → Established efficacy through quantitative precision-recall measures and qualitative analysis of instructor interviews using a grounded theory approach.
- TweetBubble [Human-Computer Interaction]

Fall 2013-Fall 2016

A Chrome Extension for Twitter users to follow @usernames, #hashtags associations without tabs or windows.

- → Developed and deployed Chrome Extension, making it available worldwide.
- \rightarrow Conducted studies during societal events such as the Academy Awards and Super Bowl.
- → Developed ideation metrics of exploratory browsing, including Fluency, Flexibility, and Novelty.
- → Established efficacy through a mixed methods evaluation, including quantitative ideation metrics and qualitative analysis of user experience data using grounded theory.
- Event Indicators [Natural Language Processing]

Spring 2016–Fall 2016

A weakly supervised approach for extracting and clustering event indicators from Twitter social media.

- → Cleaned up event relevant tweets, filtering duplicates arising from exact matches, substrings, punctuations, etc.
- → Applied bootstrapping to acquire a variety of civil unrest event cues, starting from a single strong indicator.
- **BigSemantics** [Software Engineering]

Fall 2012–Fall 2016

A software architecture for developing meta-metadata semantics powered dynamic exploratory browsing interfaces.

- → Developed new data models, extraction rules, and presentation semantics for social media.
- → Developed a RESTful service to facilitate semantics-driven application development across a range of contexts.
- EvolutionWorks [Human-Computer Interaction, Information Retrieval]

Fall 2011–Spring 2012

A free-form, zoomable space facilitating browsing, collection, and sensemaking of research papers interconnections.

- → Developed interface for presenting papers as cards within the free-form zoomable space.
- → Developed algorithm for determining representative terms present within a cluster when the user zooms out.
- → Established efficacy through user studies, comparing the interface with tabbed browsers.
- PhotoNav [Human-Computer Interaction]

Fall 2011–Spring 2012

A mixed reality investigation for assisting pedestrian navigation through the means of photographs.

- → Developed the NavCurator application for the specification of navigation paths over maps.
- → Evaluated handheld and head-mounted displays—through user studies—for assisting pedestrian navigation.

AWARDS & ACHIEVEMENTS

• Senior Membership, IEEE

2024

• Highly Useful Review Recognition for ACM Creativity & Cognition

2024

• Spot Bonus for Scale Maximization work at Audigent

2022

Best Paper Nomination at ACM Document Engineering	2021
• Best Student Paper Nomination at ACM Document Engineering	2021
• Student Travel Grant, College of Engineering, Texas A&M	2021
• Best Teaching Assistant Nomination(s), Dept. of Computer Science and Engineering, Texas A&M	2018-2021
• Outstanding Reviewer Recognition for ACM CHI PLAY Full Papers	2019
• Academy for Future Faculty Certificate, Center for Teaching Excellence, Texas A&M	2018
• Student Travel Grant, College of Engineering, Texas A&M	2017
• Student Travel Grant, National Science Foundation	2017
• Best Paper Honorable Mention at ACM Creativity & Cognition	2015
• Student Travel Grant, College of Engineering, Texas A&M	2015
• Extra Mile Award at Samsung	2010
• Best Project Award(s) at Samsung	2008, 2010
• Best Attitude Award at Samsung	2008
• Six Sigma Green Belt at Samsung	2008

2021

PATENTS

- Jain, A., Griffiths, M., Spiegelman, M., Peng, K., and Stein, D., Predictive Pop, Inc. d/b/a Audigent. Systems and Method for Simultaneous Relevance and Variety Control in Audience Targeting. U.S. Patent Application 18/406,156, filed Jan 7, 2024.
- Subramanian, M., Bansal, R.K., Jain, A., Khandelwal, D., Agrawal, G., Solanki, N. and Thakur, P., Samsung Electronics Co Ltd, 2013. Display Device and Method for Presenting Information on Entities Displayed on Video Content. U.S. Patent Application 13/888,669, filed May 7, 2013.

Manuscripts

- 1. Jain, A., Kerne, A., Fowler, H., Seo, J., Newman, G., Lupfer, N., and Perrine, A. (2024). How Could AI Support Design Education? A Study Across Fields Fuels Situating Analytics. arXiv preprint arXiv:2404.17390.
- 2. **Jain, A.**, Kerne, A., Lupfer, N., Britain, G., Perrine, A., Choe, Y., Keyser, J., Huang, R., Seo, J., Sungkajun, A., Lightfoot, R., and McGuire, T. (2024). Indexing Analytics to Instances: How Integrating a Dashboard can Support Design Education. arXiv preprint arXiv:2404.05417.

Refereed Conference Papers

- 1. Jain, A., Kerne, A., Lupfer, N., Britain, G., Perrine, A., Choe, Y., Keyser, J., and Huang, R. Recognizing Creative Visual Design: Multiscale Design Characteristics in Free-Form Web Curation Documents. In *Proceedings of the ACM Symposium on Document Engineering (DocEng) 2021*, 1-10 [33%]. Best Paper Nomination, Best Student Paper Nomination.
- 2. Kerne, A., Lupfer, N., Linder, R., Qu, Y., Valdez, A., Jain, A., Keith, K., Carrasco, M., Vanegas, J., Billingsley, A. Free-form Web Curation: Strategies for Creative Engagement with Prior Work. In *Proceedings of the ACM Conference on Creativity & Cognition (C&C) 2017*, 380-392 [29%].

- 3. Sharma, H. N., Toups, Z. O., Dolgov, I., Kerne, A., **Jain, A.** Evaluating Display Modalities using a Mixed Reality Game. In *Proceedings of the ACM Annual Symposium on Computer-Human Interaction in Play (CHI PLAY) 2016*, 65-77 [29%].
- 4. Jain, A., Lupfer, N., Qu, Y., Linder, R., Kerne, A., Smith, S. M. Evaluating TweetBubble with Ideation Metrics of Exploratory Browsing. In *Proceedings of the ACM Conference on Creativity and Cognition (C&C) 2015*, 178-187 [28%]. Best Paper Honorable Mention Top 2%.
- 5. Wilkins, J., Järvi, J., Jain, A., Kerne, A., Kejriwal, G., Gumudavelly, V. EvolutionWorks: Towards Improved Visualization of Citation Networks. In *Proceedings of the IFIP Conference on Computer-Human Interaction (INTERACT)* 2015, 213-230 [29.9%].
- Qu, Y., Kerne, A., Lupfer, N., Linder, R., Jain, A. Metadata Type System: Integrate Presentation, Data Models
 and Extraction to Enable Exploratory Browsing Interfaces. In Proceedings of the ACM Engineering Interactive
 Computing Systems (EICS) 2014, 107-116 [18%].
- Fei, S., Webb, A. M., Kerne, A., Qu, Y., and Jain, A. Peripheral Array of Tangible NFC Tags: Positioning Portals for Embodied Trans-Surface Interaction. In Proceedings of the ACM Conference on Interactive Tabletops and Surfaces (ITS) 2013, 33-36 [29%].
- 8. Jain, A. and Singh, S. Modified Programming Language Framework for IVRS Accessibility of Graphical User Interfaces. U-Media, pp.163-167, In *Proceedings of the IEEE Conference on Ubi-Media Computing (U-Media) 2011*, 163-167 [34%].

Refereed Workshops and Extended Abstracts

- 1. Britain, G., Jain, A., Lupfer, N., Kerne, A., Perrine, A., Seo, J., Sungkajun, A. Design is (A)live: An Environment Integrating Ideation and Assessment, In *Extended Abstracts of the ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI Late-Breaking Work)* 2020, 1-8 [41.8%].
- 2. Jain, A. Measuring Creativity: Multi-Scale Visual and Conceptual Design Analysis. In *Proceedings of the ACM Conference on Creativity & Cognition (C&C) 2017*, Graduate Student Symposium, 490-495.
- 3. Jain, A., Kasiviswanathan, G., and Huang, R. Towards Accurate Event Detection in Social Media: A Weakly Supervised Approach for Learning Implicit Event Indicators. In *Proceedings of the Computational Linguistics* (COLING) Workshop on Noisy User-Generated Text (WNUT) 2016, 70-77.
- 4. Sharma, H. N., Toups, Z. O., **Jain, A.**, Kerne, A. Designing to Split Attention in a Mixed Reality Game. In *Proceedings of the ACM Annual Symposium on Computer-Human Interaction in Play (CHI PLAY) 2015*, 691-696.
- 5. Fei, S., Kerne, A., **Jain, A.**, Webb, A. M., and Qu, Y. Positioning portals with peripheral NFC tags to embody trans-surface interaction. In *Proceedings of the ACM Conference on Interactive Tabletops and Surfaces (ITS) 2013*, 317-320.

Presentations

• Cognitive Audiences: Powering the Cookieless Future

Jan 2024, May 2024

Experian Data Scientists and Business Development Leads

• Recognizing Creative Visual Design: Multiscale Design Characteristics in Free-Form Web Curation Documents

Aug 2021

DocEng'21: Document Engineering

• LiveMâché: Ideation on the Web

Sep 2020

Georgia Tech ME 6102: Designing Open Engineering Systems

• Measuring Creativity: Multi-Scale Visual and Conceptual Design Analysis

Jun 2017

C&C'17: Creativity and Cognition (Graduate Student Symposium)

• Towards Accurate Event Detection in Social Media

COLING'16: Computational Linguistics

Evaluating TweetBubble with Ideation Metrics of Exploratory Browsing

Jun 2015

Dec 2016

C&C'15: Creativity and Cognition

• Programming Language Framework for IVRS Accessibility of Graphical User Interfaces

Jul 2011

UMEDIA'11: Ubi-Media Computing

SKILLS

- Programming Languages: C, C++, Java, Python, Scala, R
- Web Programming: HTML, JavaScript, React, REST, Django, Node.js
- Big Data Technologies: Spark, Kafka, Druid, Airflow
- Machine Learning Libraries: Scikit-learn, TensorFlow, Keras
- Visualization Libraries: D3.js, Three.js, Gephi
- Research Methods: Interviews, Surveys, Observations, Workshops, Grounded Theory, Hypothesis Testing

TEACHING

- Instructor of Record, Dept. of Computer Science and Engineering, Texas A&M

Spring 2021

CSCE 121 Introduction to Program Design and Concepts (C++)

• Teaching Assistant, Dept. of Computer Science and Engineering, Texas A&M

Spring 2015–Fall 2020

CSCE 655 Human-Centered Computing

CSCE 482 Senior Capstone Design

CSCE 444 Structures of Interactive Information

CSCE 420 Artificial Intelligence

CSCE 315 Programming Studio

CSCE 206 Structured Programming (C++)

CSCE 121 Introduction to Program Design and Concepts (C++)

MENTORING

• Industry Mentoring, Audigent, Amobee, and Samsung

 $2009\hbox{--}2011,\ 2022\hbox{--} Present$

Mentor software, data, and full-stack engineers on various aspects of system development, including ideation, architectural design, coding, debugging, evaluation, documentation, and presentation.

• Gabriel Britain, Undergraduate Student in Computer Science, Texas A&M

Fall 2019–Spring 2020

Research: Design analytics dashboards and their integration with a multiscale design environment.

- Hannah Fowler, Undergraduate Student in Computer Science, Texas A&M

Spring 2018–Fall 2018

Research: A grounded theory analysis of design instructors' teaching and assessment practices and needs.

- Aaron Perrine, Undergraduate Student in Computer Science, Texas A&M

Spring 2018–Fall 2018

Research: Design analytics dashboards and their integration with a multiscale design environment.

- Alex Stacy, Undergraduate Student in Computer Science, Texas A&M

Fall 2016

Research: BigSemantics-based wrappers for extracting and presenting information from social media.

SERVICE

•	Reviewer	2015–	Present
	Recognition for Outstanding / Highly Useful Reviews at M	Multiple Venues	
	ACM CHI 2024, 2022, 2021, 2020, 2019, 2017, 2016 ACM DIS 2022, 2021, 2020, 2019, 2018, 2016 ACM C&C 2024, 2021, 2019, 2015 ACM CHI PLAY 2024, 2019, 2018, 2017 ACM CSCW 2022, 2020, 2018 ACM ISWC 2023 ACM ISS 2023 ACM ICMI 2021 CogSci 2021, 2019 EAI MobiHealth 2020		
•	Associate Chair		2025
	ACM CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing S	ystems	
•	Associate Chair		2021
	ACM Creativity & Cognition		
•	Judge, Student Research Week		2021
	Texas A&M University		
•	Registration Chair		2019
	ACM Creativity & Cognition		
•	Student Volunteer		2012
	Design Computing and Cognition		
R	EFERENCES		
	Professor Department of Computer Science and Engineering Texas A&M University	Dr. Ruihong Huang Associate Professor Department of Computer Science and Engineering Texas A&M University	

Professor Department of Psychology Texas A&M University ⋈ stevesmith@tamu.edu

Dr. Steven M. Smith

Dr. Jinsil Seo

Associate Professor Department of Visualization Texas A&M University \bowtie hwaryoung@tamu.edu